The Duane A. Davidson Papers
Yale University Music Library
The Duane A. Davidson Papers
1955-1977
MSS 17
Yale University Music Library
4
(6 boxes)
Music, correspondence and other papers, and photographs by the American composer Duane A. Davidson (1934 or 1935-1964)
Davidson, Duane A. (Duane Andrew), 1934-1964
Conditions Governing Access
The Papers are open to researchers by appointment. There are no restricted materials in the collection. Please contact the Special Collections staff to schedule an appointment.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Duane A. Davidson Papers were established in the Music Library of Yale University in 1976 by Davidson's parents, Mr. and Mrs. Harley Davidson (no relation to the motorcycle manufacturer).
Arrangement
In 2 series as follows: I. Miscellaneous items. II. Musical works of Duane A. Davidson.
Scope and Contents
The Duane A. Davidson Papers contain sketches, manuscript scores, and published editions of Davidson's musical works, including orchestral music, chamber works, piano pieces, songs, and choral music. Davidson's life and work are further documented by: programs, press releases, and reviews; correspondence with Quincy Porter; writings by Davidson; and sound recordings.
Biographical / Historical
Duane A. Davidson was born in Rural Retreat, Virginia in 1934 or 1935. He earned a B.A. from Emory and Henry College in Virginia, and a master's degree in music in 1960 from Yale, where he was a student of Quincy Porter. His further studies included lessons with Leon Kirchner at Tanglewood in 1960. Davidson received awards for several of his works. In 1953 he was named the outstanding young composer during Pan American week. Psalm 150 won for him the Block Award, and in June 1960 he gained first prize in the Queen Elizabeth International Contest of the Wind Music Society in London. His Jazz Implications won first prize in the Composer's Competition in London in June 1960, and was premiered on the BBC. His works have been performed in London, Rome, Graz, Tanglewood, and Middlebury College in Vermont. Duane Davidson died in Washington, D.C. in December 1964.
Cantatas, Secular -- Scores; Composers -- Correspondence; Music -- United States -- 20th Century; Piano music; Songs; String quartets -- Scores; Davidson, Duane A. (Duane Andrew), 1934-1964; Porter, Quincy, 1897-1966
- Miscellaneous items, Series I
  - Davidson, Duane A., 3 items (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 2 autograph letters signed, to Quincy Porter, 1960 Jun 8, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 1 typed letter signed, to Quincy Porter, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Reviews of Davidson's works, photocopies, 1963-1976; 8 items (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Press releases, brief biographies, in part, photocopies, 1965-1976; 4 items (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Photographs of presentation of 52 of Duane's manuscripts by Harley Davidson (father) to Dean Philip Nelson of the Yale University School of Music, 1976 Nov 18; 5 items (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Programs including Davidson's works, in part, photocopies, 1958-1977; 16 items (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Davidson, Duane A. Reflections of Duane A. Davidson, c1966; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 6)
    General
    (poetry)
- Musical works of Duane A. Davidson, Series II
  - Petite Pièce, 1955 Mar; 3 items (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Holograph signed, in ink, score.
    Holograph signed, in ink, in part photocopies, parts, 2 copies.
  - Three Songs for Gabrielle, 1955 Dec; 2 items (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Holograph signed, in ink and pencil, piano-vocal score.
    Photocopy of above.
  - Introduction - Berceuse and Rondino, 1956 Jul 8; 7 items (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Holograph signed, in pencil, for horn and piano [originally entitled Suite No. 2: I. Prelude, II. Berceuse, III. Rondino]
    Prelude for horn and piano.
    Berceuse for oboe and piano, 2 copies.
    Berceuse, oboe part.
    Holograph signed, in ink, for horn and piano.
    Photocopy of holograph signed, horn part.
  - Sonatine for oboe and piano, 1956 Jul; 3 items (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Holograph in pencil.
    Photocopy of above, 2 copies.
  - Summer Day, 1957 Jan 9; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Holograph signed, in pencil, piano-vocal score.
  - Pretense, 1957 Jan 10; 2 items (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Sonata for horn and piano, 1957 Aug; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Holograph signed, in ink.
  - Divertissement en Fa, 1957; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Holograph signed, in pencil, for oboe, horn, and bassoon.
  - Cantata No. 1: Melora's Song, 1958 Sep; 5 items (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Holograph signed, in ink and pencil, for soprano, woodwinds, and piano.
    Holograph signed, in ink, for soprano, woodwind quintet, and piano.
    Vocal score for rehearsal only photocopy of signed holograph.
    Holograph signed, in pencil, sketch.
  - Cantata No. 1: Song from a Green Hill [substitute lyrics], 2 items (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Holograph signed, in ink and pencil.
  - String Quartet No. 1, 1958 Dee 31; 4 items (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Holograph signed, in pencil.
    Photocopy of holograph signed, parts.
    Holograph in pencil, sketch
    Photocopy of holograph signed, with note about revisions in score dated 1960 Apr.
  - Fugue in C Minor, 3 items (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Holograph signed, in ink, for keyboard instrument.
  - Little Fugue in C Minor, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Holograph signed, in pencil, for string quartet.
    Photocopy, parts.
  - Introduction - Song and Parody, 1958; 3 items (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Holograph, signed in ink and pencil, for harp and bassoon.
    Parts, original and photocopy reduction of bassoon, and photocopy reduction of manuscript for harp only.
  - Danse Rituelle, 1959 Jan; 1 item (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Holograph signed, in pencil, 4 hands.
  - The West Wind, 1959 Jan; 3 items (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Holograph signed, in ink, piano-vocal score.
    Holograph in pencil, sketch.
  - Madrigal, 1959 Mar 7; 3 items (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Holograph signed in pencil, for chorus, unaccompanied.
    Holograph signed in ink, for chorus (SATB), unaccompanied.
  - Jazz Implications, 1959 Apr; 7 items (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
    Holograph signed, in ink and pencil, for band.
    Holograph signed, in ink, for band, 2 copies.
    Holograph signed in ink, parts, 3 copies, in part, photocopies.
  - Cantata No. 2: Journey of Paradoxes, 1959 Oct 17; 11 items (Box 2, Folder 6-8)
    Holograph signed in pencil, piano-vocal score.
    Holograph signed, in ink, for soprano and orchestra, 5 copies, in part, photocopies.
    Holograph in ink, parts, 3 copies.
  - Fugue in F Minor, 1959 Oct 17; 6 items (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Holograph signed, in pencil, for keyboard instrument.
    Photocopy reduction of above.
    Manuscript, in pencil, for woodwind quartet.
    Parts, for woodwind quartet, 2 copies.
  - Sonata, piano, no. 1, 1960 Jan; 3 items (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Holograph signed in pencil, sketch.
  - Introduction and Dance No. 1, 1960 Mar; 3 items (Box 6, Folder 1)
    Holograph signed in ink and pencil, score.
    Holograph in ink, score.
  - Introduction and Dance, 1960 Aug; 2 items (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Holograph, sketches.
  - Psalm 150: Hallelujah, 1960 Nov; 3 items (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Holograph signed, in ink, for chorus (SATB), unaccompanied.
    Photocopy of holograph, sketch.
  - Le 14 Juillet, no date; 3 items (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Holograph signed, in ink, fantasy for piano.
    "To Gérard, bonne chance pour '59-'60, Duane"--verso of title page.
    Holograph in ink, sketch.
  - Cantata No. 3: The Execution, 1961; 13 items (Box 3, Folder 6-9)
    Holograph signed, in pencil, for soprano, tenor, chorus of 4 alto voices, and chamber orchestra.
    Holograph signed, in ink, of above.
    Holograph signed, in ink, rehearsal reduction for 2 pianos.
    Holograph signed, in ink, vocal parts, orchestra reduction, 5 copies, in part, photocopies.
    Holograph signed, in ink, parts.
    Photocopies of above.
    Holograph in ink and pencil, sketch.
    Holograph and typescript, synopsis of scenes.
  - Stravaganza I, 1961; 10 items (Box 4, Folder 1-3)
    Holograph signed, in ink, for trombone and orchestra.
    Holograph signed, in ink, for trombone and orchestra, revised version, 2 copies.
    Holograph signed, in ink, piano reduction.
    Holograph signed, in ink, solo trombone part, 3 copies, in part, photocopies.
    Manuscript in ink, parts, some duplicates, in part, photocopies.
    Holograph in pencil, sketches.
  - Berceuse for Ann and Child, 1962 Jan 3; 3 items (Box 4, Folder 4)
    Parts, 2 copies, in part, photocopies.
  - Choreographies, 1962; 3 items (Box 4, Folder 5)
    Photocopy of holograph signed, a concerto for oboe and orchestra, score.
    Holograph in ink and pencil, sketch of movement I.
    Holograph in ink and pencil, sketch of movements I and II.
  - Psalm 23, 1962-1964; 6 items (Box 4, Folder 6-7)
    Holograph signed, in ink, for chorus (SATB) and piano.
    Holograph signed)in pencil, for chorus (SATB) and orchestra, score.
  - Chorale, Introduction and Psalm (Box 4, Folder 6-7)
    Holograph signed, in ink, for chorus (SATB) and orchestra, score [his Psalm 23]
    Holograph, in part, signed, in part photocopies, parts.
  - French Suite for Small Orchestra, 1964; 5 items (Box 5, Folder 1-3)
    Holograph in ink, in part, signed, in part, photocopies, parts. Some duplicates.
    Holograph in pencil, score.
    Photocopy of holograph of score.
  - Cantata No. 4: The Queen's Marie, no date; 3 items (Box 5, Folder 4)
    Holograph in ink, score, incomplete.
  - Composition exercises, no date; 16 items (Box 5, Folder 5)
    Holographs in ink and pencil.
  - Joanna, no date; 2 items (Box 5, Folder 6)
    Holograph in ink, synopsis of opera in 3 acts.
    Holograph in ink and pencil, various sketches.
  - Psalm 100, no date; 1 item (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Quartet for Woodwinds, no date; 1 item (Box 5, Folder 8)
    Photocopy of score.
  - Sketches, no date; 1 item (Box 5, Folder 9)
    Holographs in ink and pencil, various sketches.
  - String Quartet No. 2, no date; 1 item (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Theme and Variations, no date; 1 item (Box 5, Folder 11)
    For woodwind quintet, photocopy of parts.
  - Various sketched and libretti, no date; 16 items (Box 5, Folder 12)
    In part, holographs in ink and pencil.
  - Tapes of performances of selected musical works of Duane A. Davidson., 5 items (Box 6)
  - Jazz Implications, 1977 Feb 24-25 (Box 6)
    U.S. Naval Academy Band, Lt. John R, Bledsoe, USN, conductor, 7.5 IPS.
  - Instrumental works (Box 6)
    Piano sonata, String Quartet No. 1, Sonatina for Oboe and Piano, Sonata for Trombone and Piano, 7,5 IPS, 2 copies.
  - Choral works (Box 6)
    Chorale and Psalm 23, Madrigal, Cantata No. 1, Cantata No. 2, 2 copies.